Guide to the J. M. Barrie Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Writings, 1876–1954; Series II; 16.5; 35 boxes
  - Plays and Other Scripts
    - Half an Hour
      - Autograph introduction, circa 1913 (Box 37, Folder 854)
      - Autograph manuscript, signed, circa 1913 (Box 37, Folder 855)
        With note: "As revised for book form."
      - Autograph list of changes, circa 1913 (Box 37, Folder 856)
      - Autograph manuscript, circa 1913 (Box 37, Folder 857)
        Leaves numbered 19, 28, and 34.
      - Typescripts with autograph revisions, circa 1913 (Box 37, Folder 858)
        Two scripts in gray paper wrappers.
      - Typescript with manuscript annotations, circa 1913 (Box 37, Folder 859)
        Missing wrappers and pages 1-5.
      - Typescript with autograph revisions, circa 1913 (Box 37, Folder 860)
        In gray paper wrappers.
      - Typescript with autograph and manuscript revisions, circa 1913 (Box 37, Folder 861)
      - Typescript with autograph revisions and revisions in Irene Vanbrugh's hand, 1913 (Box 37, Folder 862)
        Accompanied by one sheet of manuscript music in an unidentified hand. Bound in green morocco with author, title, and "I.V. [Irene Vanbrugh] 1913" gold-stamped on front cover.
      - Typescript (incomplete) with autograph revisions and other revisions in an unidentified hand, circa 1913 (Box 37, Folder 863)
        Missing wrappers and the final pages.
    - The House of Fear, 1916 November 19 (Box 37, Folder 864)
      Two typescripts with autograph revisions of a one-act play originally titled "The Fight for Mr. Lapraik." In gray paper wrappers.
    - How Men Love
      On July 4, 1914, Barrie took a group of friends on a trip to Hertfordshire to make a film he hoped to use in a proposed revue, and it is possible that this typescript was prepared for use at that time. The characters are Mrs. Patrick Campbell, George Bernard Shaw, Lord Howard de Walden, William Archer, and G. K. Chesterton.
      - Two typescripts with autograph revisions, [1914] (Box 37, Folder 865)
        Prologue to be delivered by Mrs. Patrick Campbell. In gray paper wrappers.
      - Typescript describing action to be filmed, [1914] (Box 37, Folder 866)
        Leaves 3 and 4.
    - Ibsen's Ghost
      A one-act play written in 1891 and produced May 30, 1891, at Toole's Theatre, London. Sixteen copies of the play were privately printed in January 1939 by George Lionel Seymour Dawson-Damer, Viscount Carlow, at his Corvinus Press.
      - Autograph manuscript, [1893] (Box 38, Folder 867)
        Accompanied by one half-sheet of manuscript music signed WR, and one leaf of script in verse, in an unidentified hand, titled "Ibsen."
      - Typescript with autograph corrections, 1932 (Box 38, Folder 868)
        Autograph inscription on first flyleaf: "Cynthia [Asquith] from JMB May 9, 1932." Bound in red leather.
      - Typescript, 1932 (Box 38, Folder 869)
        Autograph inscription on title page: "T.L.G. from JMB. Oct 1932." Thomas Lennox Gilmour added autograph notes on first two flyleaves: "One of six copies" and one on the history of the play. Autograph note by Viscount Carlow on first flyleaf: "It was from this copy that the edition of 16 copies produced at the Corvinus Press was printed. Carlow 1939." Bound in tan cloth.
      - Typescript, 1932 (Box 38, Folder 870)
        Autograph inscription on second flyleaf: "To Irene Vanbrugh from her affectionate friend J. M. Barrie May 1932." Bound in tan cloth.
      - Typescript, [1932?] (Box 38, Folder 871)
    - If There Had Been No War, undated (Box 38, Folder 872)
      Autograph notes for a play; subtitled "(The 'Men of 50' idea turned round)."
    - A Kiss for Cinderella
      A three-act play produced March 16, 1916, at Wyndham's Theatre, London.
      - Typescripts of Acts I-III, with autograph revisions, circa 1916 (Box 38, Folder 873)
        With twenty numbered leaves of autograph manuscript laid in: Act I (1-6); Act II (1-4, 30-35); Act III (1-3). In gray paper wrappers.
      - Typescripts of various acts with autograph revisions, circa 1916 (Box 38, Folder 874)
        Two typescripts of Act I, one of Act II and two of Act III; four in gray paper wrappers, one in brown paper wrappers.
      - Typescript leaves, circa 1916 (Box 38, Folder 875)
        Leaves from other typescripts with autograph revisions: Act II (3-11); Act III (8-10, 21-26); Act III (7 unnumbered).
      - Contract between Barrie and Leon M. Lion, 1925 March 10 (Box 38, Folder 876)
        For productions in "South Africa including the territories of Rhodesia Portuguese East Africa and East and South West Africa" for one year.
    - The Ladies' Shakespeare
      A three-act parody of Shakespeare's The Taming of the Shrew told from a feminist perspective. It was produced by Maude Adams in October 1914 in Rochester, New York, and subsequently toured in the 1914-1915 season.
      - Typescript, signed, with autograph revisions and autograph manuscript pages, circa 1914 (Box 38, Folder 877)
        One printed page from the Temple Shakespeare is attached to page 35 of the script.
      - Typescript and printed pages pasted into a signed notebook, circa 1914 (Box 38, Folder 878)
        Manuscript revisions and note (on free endpaper) in an unidentified hand, presumed to be that of Herbert Beerbohm Tree: "If lost to be returned to H. B. Tree His Majesty's Theatre." The printed pages are from The Chiswick Shakespeare. Bound in half cloth with marbled covers.
    - The Legend of Leonora / The Adored One
      A three-act comedy produced September 4, 1913, at the Duke of York's Theatre, London. In a revised form, as The Legend of Leonora, it was produced at the Empire Theatre in New York on January 5, 1914. A variation of Act I, titled "Seven Women" is published in The Plays of J. M. Barrie (London, 1928). The entire play, The Legend of Leonora, was published in The Works of J. M. Barrie (New York, 1941), v. 17.
      - Autograph manuscript, signed and dated, 1913 January 28 (Box 39, Folder 879)
      - Typescript, Act I, circa 1913 (Box 39, Folder 880)
        Four typescripts, three with autograph revisions. Each typescript of Act I is a different version of the act with a different title. Typescript 4 is signed on the title page. In gray paper wrappers.
      - Typescript, Acts II and III, circa 1913 (Box 39, Folder 881)
        One typescript, with autograph revisions, of each act. Act II is a different version of the play, not related to any of the typescripts or to the manuscript. No combination of these typescripts makes a complete play. In gray paper wrappers.
    - The Little Minister
      A four-act play based on Barrie's 1891 novel, produced on September 13, 1897, at the Empire Theatre, Washington.
      - One unnumbered leaf of autograph manuscript from Act IV, circa 1897 (Box 39, Folder 882)
      - Typescript, Acts I-IV, circa 1897 (Box 39, Folder 883)
        Two typescripts of Act I, one of Act II, two of Act III, and two of Act IV, with autograph revisions and manuscript revisions in an unidentified hand. These typescripts were probably used in the first American production of the play.
      - Typescript, Acts I-III, circa 1897 (Box 39, Folder 884)
        Typescripts with autograph corrections and additions in Act II, and manuscript stage directions in an unidentified hand in Acts I and III. In gray paper wrappers with Addison Bright's name and address written on the cover of each act.
      - Typescript, Acts I, II, and IV, circa 1897 (Box 39, Folder 885)
        Typescripts with autograph corrections and additions. In gray paper wrappers.
      - Score for a string quintet, circa 1897 (Box 39, Folder 886)
        Manuscript, in unidentified hand, of a score by William Furst for the American production. Inscribed on title page: "Score String Quintett 'The Little Minister' Music by Wm. Furst Empire Theatre. N.Y. City."
      - Dialogue quotations, most from The Little Minister, 1898–1900 (Box 40, Folder 887)
        Thirteen short quotations from Barrie scripts, copied and signed by actors including Winifred Emery, Minnie Brooke, Ellen Terry, Violet Bruce, and Cyril Maude.
      - Screenplay by Jane Murfin, 1934 (Box 40, Folder 888)
        Duplicator copy of screenplay script issued by RKO Studios, Inc., used and annotated by English actor Donald Crisp.
    - Mary Rose
      A three-act play produced on April 22, 1920, at the Haymarket Theatre, London.
      - Autograph manuscript, circa 1920 (Box 40, Folder 889)
        Titled: "Poor Barbara Lucy Joanne (Left-Hander)" with autograph inscription on first page: "(This is the first draft of Mary Rose. It is much altered in the second M.S. 'Left Hander' means that my right hand gave out. I think this and anything subsequently was written with my left hand. JMB 1929)" Accompanied by an autograph letter, signed, from Cynthia Asquith to "Mr. Scribner" dated November 28, 1940.
        Gift of Henry C. Taylor (Yale 1917), 1948.
      - Autograph manuscript, circa 1920 (Box 40, Folder 890-891)
        Presentation inscription: "To Cynthia Asquith from J. M. Barrie (the M.S. of 'Mary Rose') May 9, 1920." Accompanied by four leaves of autograph manuscript numbered 15, 16, 17, and 17 which correspond to leaves 17, 18, 19, and 20 of Act II of the autograph manuscript. Bound in blue morocco by Douglas Cockerell & Son; signed "DC & Son 1929" and enclosed in a wooden case.
      - Typescript, Acts I-III, circa 1920 (Box 40, Folder 892)
        Typescript with autograph revisions; many leaves are written on both sides. In gray paper wrappers.
      - Typescript, Acts I-III, circa 1920 (Box 41, Folder 893)
        Acts I and III typescript and Act II typescript carbon, commercially bound with "Mary Rose" stamped in gold on front cover. Stamped on title page: "From Charles Frohman, Empire Theatre Building, Broadway & 40th Street, New York." Inserted in front: cast list and scene synopsis from the Empire Theatre production starring Ruth Chatterton, December 22, 1920. Contains lighting and property plots.
      - Typescript, Acts I-III, circa 1920 (Box 41, Folder 894-896)
        Six copies of Act I, four copies of Act II, two copies of Act III, all with autograph revisions. Some copies have ground plans. In gray paper wrappers.
    - Men of Fifty, undated (Box 41, Folder 897)
    - The New Word
      A one-act comedy produced March 22, 1915, at the Duke of York's Theatre, London, and May 14, 1917, at the Empire Theatre, New York.
      - Autograph manuscript, signed, circa 1915 (Box 41, Folder 898)
      - Typescript, with autograph revisions, circa 1915 (Box 41, Folder 899)
      - Typescript, circa 1915 (Box 41, Folder 900)
        From the American production, with cast list from program inserted in front. Manuscript notes revisions in red ink by "E Broadley" and pencil notes in an unidentified hand.
    - Old Friends, circa 1910 (Box 41, Folder 901)
      Autograph manuscript, signed, of a one-act play produced March 1, 1910, at the Duke of York's Theatre, London.
    - The Old Lady Shows Her Medals, circa 1917 (Box 41, Folder 902)
      Typescript with autograph revisions of a one-act play produced April 17, 1917, at the New Theatre, London. Alternate title: "Charwomen & the War." In gray paper wrappers.
    - The 1000 N'S, circa 1904 (Box 41, Folder 903)
      Autograph notes for a play. The "N" refers to "Nightingale," according to Denis Mackail in his The Story of J. M. B. (London: Peter Davies, 1941), pages 358, 359, and 386).
    - The Origin of Harlequin, circa 1918 (Box 41, Folder 904)
      Autograph manuscript of stage directions and script for a one-act ballet produced at a charity matinee on June 28, 1918, at Wyndham's Theatre, London. It was evidently written for Rosy Rapture, the Pride of the Beauty Chorus, but no reference appears in the typescript of that revue in the Barrie Collection. A similar ballet, without words, is Scene 4 in Reconstructing a Crime.
    - A Page from Dumas, undated (Box 41, Folder 905)
      Two autograph manuscript versions of a one-act play adapted from an incident in The Three Musketeers. Accompanied by one leaf and three pages of autograph notes.
    - Pantaloon: A Domestic Drama
      A one-act play produced April 5, 1905, at the Duke of York's Theatre, London, as a curtain raiser for Alice-Sit-by-the-Fire.
      - Autograph manuscript, incomplete, circa 1905 (Box 42, Folder 906)
      - Autograph manuscript, circa 1905 (Box 42, Folder 907)
        With autograph revisions; bound in blue morocco by Morrell, London. Inscribed on title page: "To Gerald du Maurier from his friend J. M. Barrie Mar 15 1906."
      - Typescripts, circa 1905 (Box 42, Folder 908)
        Two typescripts with autograph revisions; one typescript is signed.
      - Typescript, circa 1905 (Box 42, Folder 909)
        With manuscript annotations in an unidentified hand.
    - Peter Pan, or the Boy Who Wouldn't Grow Up
      The play was first produced on December 27, 1904, at The Duke of York's Theatre, London, but not published as a play until 1928. Material is filed in chronological order.
      - "Fairy", 1903 October 14 (Box 42, Folder 910)
        Autograph notes for a play, accompanied by ten leaves, some written on both sides, of undated autograph "Revise notes."
      - Autograph manuscript leaves numbered 8, 30, 31 and 32, circa 1904 (Box 42, Folder 911)
        From an early version of the play.
      - Typescript, "Anon," Act III, 1904 (Box 42, Folder 912)
        Two typescripts, with autograph revisions, of Act III of the three-act version of the play. Many leaves are written on both sides.
      - Autograph manuscript, Act III, scenes 2 and 4, 1904–1905 (Box 42, Folder 913)
        Scene 2 is similar to the text of the same scene in the 1904-1905 three-act version (typescript) of the play entitled "Anon." Most of the text of Scene 4 is published in Roger Lancelyn Green's Fifty Years of Peter Pan (London: Peter Davies, 1954), pages 66-67.
      - Typescript, "Anon," Acts I-III, 1904–1905 (Box 42, Folder 914-916)
        The three-act version of the play, with manuscript revisions in an unidentified hand and interleaved with lighting plots, stage business, and prompt cues in several unidentified hands. First preliminary leaf: "A Note On the Acting of a Fairy Play." Used in the 1904-1905 production. In gray paper wrappers.
      - Typescript, "Anon," Scene 5, 1904–1905 (Box 42, Folder 917)
        With autograph revisions. A version or possible ending of the early version of the play, this leaf could be the variant copy Roger Lancelyn Green speaks of in his Fifty Years of Peter Pan (London: Peter Davies, 1954).
      - Typescript, Act I, 1905 (Box 42, Folder 918)
        From the five-act American production, in gray paper wrappers. Second preliminary leaf: "A Note On the Acting of a Fairy Play"; published in Roger Lancelyn Green's Fifty Years of Peter Pan (London: Peter Davies, 1954), page 105.
      - Typescript, Acts II-V, 1905 (Box 42, Folder 919-920)
        Two typescripts (variants) with autograph revisions, from the five-act version, prepared for the first American production in Washington, November 1905. One typescript is accompanied by a carbon copy of Acts III and IV.
      - Typescript, Act III, 1905 (Box 42, Folder 921)
        From the five-act version. In a gray paper wrappers.
      - Typescript, Act III (The Lagoon), 1905 (Box 42, Folder 922)
        From the five-act version.
      - Typescript, Act III (The Lagoon), 1905 (Box 42, Folder 923)
        With autograph revisions, from the five-act version.
      - Act V, 1905 June 13 (Box 43, Folder 924)
        From the five-act American version, in gray paper wrappers.
      - "Complete Score of Overture and Incidental Music" by John Crook and Gustav Saenger, [1904] (Box 43, Folder 925)
        Manuscript, in unidentified hand, of a condensed score featuring performance notes and markings. For the Charles Frohman production starring Maude Adams with music by John Crook, of the Duke of York's Theatre, London, and Gustav Saenger, of the Empire Theatre.
      - "Notes to accompany sketch for curtain", 1907 (Box 43, Folder 926)
        Autograph notes describing the curtain to be used in the 1908 production of Peter Pan. The curtain, designed to resemble a sampler, was a gift from Barrie to Charles Frohman. An image of the curtain appears in Roger Lancelyn's Fifty Years of Peter Pan (London: Peter Davies, 1954).
      - "Twenty Years After", 1908 (Box 43, Folder 927)
        Autograph manuscript, incomplete, of an epilogue to the play Peter Pan. Produced as "An After-thought" on one night only, February 22, 1908, at the Duke of York's Theatre, London. Accompanied by five pages of autograph notes including ideas for sequels to the Peter Pan story and for the development of the character of Peter Pan.
      - "An After-thought", 1908 (Box 43, Folder 928)
        Autograph manuscript, with revisions, of an epilogue to the play Peter Pan, with an autograph inscription on the first leaf: "To Hilda Trevelyan, my incomparable Wendy, from J. M. B. March 1908." It was produced on one night only, February 22, 1908, at the Duke of York's Theatre, London. Published in When Wendy Grew Up, an Afterthought (Edinburgh: Nelson, 1957). Accompanied by a signed manuscript in the hand of Hilda Trevelyan explaining how the play came to be written and produced and how the manuscript was given to her, and an undated typed transcript in an orange wrapper.
      - "An After-thought", 1908 (Box 43, Folder 929)
        Typescript, with autograph revisions and manuscript revisions in Hilda Trevelyan's hand; in gray paper wrappers. Published in When Wendy Grew Up, an Afterthought (Edinburgh: Nelson, 1957). Accompanied by a typed letter, signed, to Sydney Blow from the Assistant Comptroller (name illegible) in the Lord Chamberlain's office (May 22, 1956).
      - Synopsis, 1908 (Box 43, Folder 930)
        Autograph manuscript with notes on first and last leaves: "I think this was done as a leaflet for the Paris production" and "Written for the Vaudeville Theatre, Paris where (translated into French) it was given away with the programmes. The London company played it. [June 1908] J.M.B." The French translation appeared in a twelve-page booklet titled "L'histoire de Peter Pan, ou le petit garcon qui ne voulait pas grandir."
      - "Conductor Score", circa 1910 (Box 43, Folder 931)
        Manuscript score in an unidentified hand of incidental music by John Crook, with an autograph inscription by Irene Boucicault to George Barnes.
      - Speech for Hilda Trevelyan, 1912 (Box 43, Folder 932)
        Autograph manuscript of a speech written by Barrie and probably delivered by Hilda Trevelyan at the Playgoers' Club "Peter Pan Dinner" on December 22, 1912; accompanied by the printed program for the dinner.
      - Scenario for a film version, undated (Box 43, Folder 933)
        Autograph manuscript leaves numbered 30, 31, 45, 53½, [54], 58-61.
      - Scenario for a film version, 1920 (Box 43, Folder 934)
        Typescript, with autograph inscription on title page: "Private Property - J. M. Barrie"; in gray paper wrappers. Accompanied by a typed transcript of a note to Maude Adams (original note not present).
      - "Scenario for film of Peter Pan or the Boy who Wouldn't Grow Up", 1920 December 28 (Box 43, Folder 935)
        Typescript with autograph revision and note to typist; in gray paper wrappers.
      - "Scenario for film of Peter Pan or the Boy who Wouldn't Grow Up", 1921 (Box 43, Folder 936)
        Two typescripts (variants) with autograph revisions; in gray paper wrappers.
      - "Scenario for a proposed Film Of Peter Pan or The Boy Who Wouldn't Grow Up", 1921 (Box 43, Folder 937)
        Two typescripts (variants) with autograph revisions in one; in gray paper wrappers. Published in Roger Lancelyn Green's Fifty Years of Peter Pan (London: Peter Davies, 1954).
      - "Jas Hook at Eton, or The Solitary", 1925 Jan (Box 43, Folder 938)
        Autograph manuscript of a short story originally written for publication in The Flying Carpet, which was replaced by "Neil and Tintinnabulum." It appears later in a speech, "Capt. Hook at Eton," delivered by Barrie to the First Hundred at Eton on July 7, 1927.
      - "The Blot on Peter Pan", 1926 April 9
        A short story which varies from the text published in The Treasure Ship: a Book of Prose and Verse, edited by Cynthia Asquith (London: S. W. Partridge & Co., 1926).
        - Autograph manuscript, signed and dated, 1926 April 9 (Box 44, Folder 939)
          Accompanied by page 5 of another manuscript version of the story.
        - Typescript with autograph revisions, 1926 April 9 (Box 44, Folder 940)
      - "The Truth about Peter Pan", 1926 (Box 44, Folder 941)
        Autograph manuscript written for The Treasure Ship: a Book of Prose and Verse.
      - "Capt. Hook at Eton", 1927 (Box 44, Folder 942)
        Autograph manuscript, signed, of a speech based on a short story "Jas Hook at Eton" and delivered to the First Hundred at Eton College on July 7, 1927. Published in the London Times, July 8, 1927. and in M'Connachie and J. M. B. (London: Peter Davies Limited, 1938). Accompanied by a typescript of the speech with autograph revisions.
      - "To the Five", 1928 (Box 44, Folder 943)
        Preface/dedication prepared for the publication of the play. Accompanied by leaves 4, 5, 6, 7, and 15 of another manuscript version of the "dedication" and by one leaf of notes.
      - "To the Five", undated (Box 44, Folder 944)
        Autograph manuscript, with pages numbered; pages present here: 1-4, 6-7, 13, 13, 14-17.
      - "M.S. of Peter Pan. The only one in existence so far as I know", 1928 July 18 (Box 44, Folder 945)
        Autograph manuscript, signed, of the five-act version prepared for publication. The sixteen preliminary leaves contain Barrie's dedication/preface "To the Five," dated May 9, 1928. There are alterations in the work as published. The title inscribed on the flyleaf continues "to Cynthia Asquith from her affectionate J. M. Barrie Dec 1928" with a second presentation inscription on verso of free front endpaper: "for Simon Asquith from his mother Cynthia Asquith." Bound in brown morocco by Douglas Cockerell & Son; signed "DC & Son 1928" and enclosed in a wooden box.
      - Acts I-IV of the five-act version, 1928 (Box 44, Folder 946)
        Typescript with autograph revisions.
      - "Pirate Ship", undated (Box 44, Folder 947)
        Autograph manuscript of Captain Hook's opening speech from Act V. Bound in blue morocco by Morrell, London.
      - Synopsis of Act I, undated (Box 44, Folder 948)
        Typescript. This synopsis does not appear to have been written by Barrie.
      - Mimeographed script of musical based on the play, 1954 (Box 44, Folder 949)
        Produced October 19, 1954, at the Winter Garden, New York; contains prop lists, hanging plot, costume plot, etc.
    - "Play Without Words", undated (Box 45, Folder 950)
      Autograph manuscript of a skit.
    - La Politesse
      A one-act comedy produced June 28, 1918, at Wyndham's Theatre, London.
      - Autograph manuscript, signed and dated, 1918 March 23 (Box 45, Folder 951)
        Titled "Sketch - Suggested by an incident in Le Feu."
      - Typescripts with autograph revisions, circa 1918 (Box 45, Folder 952)
        Three typescripts titled "Sketch Suggested by an incident in Le Feu." In brown paper wrappers.
      - Autograph manuscript, signed, circa 1918 (Box 45, Folder 953)
        With autograph note on first page: "For benefit performance only."
      - Typescripts with autograph revisions, circa 1918 (Box 45, Folder 954)
        Two typescripts in brown paper wrappers.
      - Typescript, with autograph revisions, circa 1918 (Box 45, Folder 955)